Register of the Konstitutsionno-demokraticheskaia partiia Records, 1920-1924
Hoover Institution Archives
Konstitutsionno-demokraticheskaia partiia Records,
1920-1924
XX004
Konstitutsionno-demokraticheskaia partiia
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Minutes of meetings, resolutions, reports, and correspondence, relating to the Russian Civil War and to activities of the Konstitutsionno-demokraticheskaia partiia in exile.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Refugees.; Russians in foreign countries.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
Biographical/Historical Note
Russian liberal political party.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of material from the period after the emigration of a majority of the members of the K-D Party from Russia at the end of the Civil War. It includes minutes of meetings and reports, memoranda, correspondence, and printed matter related to matters discussed at the meetings. The first part of the collection is bound into a single volume and each page numbered consecutively; the present register describes the material by physical form and indicates the original page numbers of the documents described. The second part of the collection is unbound and arranged by type of meeting and therein chronologically.
Series Description
- TSENTRAL'NYI KOMITET, 1920-1921. (Box No. 1)
  Minutes of meetings of the Central Committee of the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody in Constantinople and Paris
- BERLINSKAIA GRUPPA, 1920-1922. (Box No. 1)
  Minutes of meetings, correspondence, and memoranda of the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody in Berlin
- KONSTANTINOPOL'SKAIA GRUPPA, 1920-1922. (Box No. 1)
  Minutes of meetings, correspondence, resolutions, and declarations of the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody in Constantinople
- BELGRADSKAIA GRUPPA, 1921-1922. (Box No. 1)
  Minutes of meetings, resolutions, reports, and correspondence of the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody in Belgrade.
- VARSHAVSKAIA GRUPPA, 1921. (Box No. 1)
  Minutes of meetings, resolutions, reports, clipping, and correspondence of the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody in Warsaw
- SOFIISKAIA GRUPPA, 1921-1923. (Box No. 1)
  Minutes of meetings and reports of the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody in Sofia
- MISCELLANEOUS DOCUMENTS, 1920-1921. (Box No. 1)
  Minutes of meetings, correspondence, membership lists, resolutions, and press releases of the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody
- PARIZHSKAIA GRUPPA, 1920-1924. (Box No. 2-3)
  Minutes of meetings and accompanying resolutions, memoranda, correspondence and newspaper clippings of the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody in Paris, arranged by type of meeting and therein chronologically
- APPENDIX.
  Original register
Container List
- TSENTRAL'NYI KOMITET, 1920-1921. Minutes of meetings
  Minutes of meetings
  - Constantinople (1-15). Meetings attended by Prince P. Dolgorukov, P. Iurenev, N. Teslenko, Prince V. Obolenskii, V. Zeeler, P. Ratner, V. Bukhshtab, V. Keller, I. Al'tshuller (Box 1.)
    - 1920 December
    - 1921
      - January
      - February
  - Paris (29-171). Meetings attended by N. Adzhemov, N. Astrov, N. Volkov, P. Gronskii, I. Demidov, Prince P. Dolgorukov, A. Kartashev, M. Mandel'shtam, P. Miliukov, V. Nabokov, B. Nol'de, Prince V. Obolenskii, S. Panina, I. Petrunkevich, F. Rodichev, S Smirnov, N. Teslenko, A. Tyrkova, 1921
    - May 10, 26-31
    - June 2
    - August 21
- BERLINSKAIA GRUPPA, 1920-1922
  - General (Box 1.)
    - "Chto delat' posle krymskoi katastrofy" (203)
    - "Zaiavlenie Berlinskoi Studencheskoi Gruppy", 14 (235)
  - Correspondence. Postcards (239)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - 1920 December
      - 19 (193)
      - 25. Includes a memorandum entitled, "Deklaratsiia gruppy sektsii molodezhy berlinskago otdela partii narodnoi svobody" (223)
    - 1922 December 14 (241)
- KONSTANTINOPOL'SKAIA GRUPPA, 1920-1922.
  Minutes of meetings attended by I. Al'tshuller, N. Bogdanov, V. Bruns, V. Bukhshtab, V. Burtsev, Prince P. Dolgorukov, I. Emelianov, K. Ermans, M. Fedorov, S. Gutnik, P. Iurenev, IU. Nikol'skii, Prince V. Obolenskii, P. Ratner, A. Svechin, N. Teslenko, I. Ushakov, V. Zeeler, V. Znamenskii. Includes material related to subject discussed at the meeting
  - 1920 December 9, 16, 23 and 30 (257-279) (Box 1.)
  - 1921
    - January 12 and 20 (285-305)
    - February
      - 11 (311)
      - 17. Includes a memorandum entitled, "Soobrazheniia po povodu chastnago soveshchaniia chlenov Uchreditel'nago Sobraniia v Parizhe... 17 Fev. 1921" (323)
      - 24 (311-329)
    - March 3, 10, 17, 24 and 31 (339-375)
    - April 7, 14, 21 and 27 (383-405)
    - May 10, 12, 19, 24 and 26 (419-443)
    - June
      - 2 (455). Includes a resolution entitled, "Rezoliutsiia po voprosu o vzaimootnosheniiakh mezhdu russkim I ob"edinnym sovetom" (465)
      - 16(467). Includes "Doklad Z. M. Znamenskago" (479)
      - 17(485)
      - 23-24(497). Includes "Rezoliutsiia"
      - 30 (507)
    - July
      - 21 (509)
      - 30 (513). Includes addenda, "Doklad Atamana Ural'skago Voiska Generala Tolstova" and "Obshchiia polozheniia prograamy politicheskago ob"edinennago komiteta"
    - August
      - 13 (525)
      - 17 (545). Includes "Rezoliutsiia"
      - 21 (557)
    - September 3, 12, 17, 24 (557-603)
    - October 8 (613)
    - November 5 (617)
    - December 3, 14 (623-625)
  - 1922
    - January 28 (635)
    - February 20 (639)
    - March 6, 13, 20 (643-661)
- BELGRADSKAIA GRUPPA, 1921-1922
  - Minutes of meetings. Attended by N. Bogdanov, M. CHubinskii, Gershun, V. Kokoshkin, A. Makletsov, V. Obolenskii, G. Sakhnovskii, S. Semenchenko, L. Tauber, V. Zen'kovskii, L. Zverev (Box 1.)
    - 1921
      - April 24 (673. Includes letter to Prince P. Dolgorukov
      - May
        - 8 (681)
        - 15 (687)
        - 22 (689). Includes addendum, "Doklad Obshchemu Sobraniiu Iugoslavianskoi gruppy partii k.-d...."
        - 29 (706)
      - June 29 (715)
      - July 13 (719)
      - August 10, 24 (721-727)
      - October 5 (731)
      - November 21 (737)
      - December 13 (739)
    - 1922 January 12 (741)
  - Resolution, "Rezoliutsiia Belgradskago komiteta" (669)
- VARSHAVSKAIA GRUPPA, 1921
  - General (Box 1.)
    - "O taktike partii, mnenie varshavskoi gruppy partii k-d" (249)
    - "Rezoliutsii sobraniia predstavitelei pravoslavnykh prikhodov v Pol'she, priniatyia 8 sentiabria 1921 goda v g. Varshave, o pravovom polozhenii Pravoslavnoi Tsrkvi v Pol'she" (786)
  - Clipping, Ukrainska Tribuna, 1921
  - Correspondence, Butenko, P., 1921 February-September (753-761, 775-783)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1921
    - March 30 (265)
    - May 31 (769)
- SOFIISKAIA GRUPPA, 1921-1923.
  Minutes of meetings attended by V. Brunst, M. D'iakonov D. Meisner, K. Parchevskii, K. Sokolov, V. Snegirev, F. Tatarinov, V. Tolli, and V. Zav'ialov
  - 1921 (Box 1.)
    - July 26 (279)
    - August
      - 1 (795). Includes addendum, "Zapiska sofiiskoi gruppy...po povodu nekotorykh osnovnykh voprosov programmy I taktiki" (831)
      - 5 (799)
      - 19 (803)
      - 30 (819)
  - 1922 January 17 (857). Includes addendum, "Zapiska sofiiskoi gruppy...o taktike gruppy chlenov partii v soveshchanii chlenov uchreditel'nago sobraniia" (861)
  - 1923 August 23 (809)
- MISCELLANEOUS DOCUMENTS, 1920-1921
  - Circular letter re convocation of Congress, 1920? (1033) (Box 1.)
  - Correspondence. Includes letters of Partiia Narodnoi Svobody to Alexandre Millerand; from N. Astrov, E. Kedrin, A. Makletsov, E. Miller, V. Nabokov, V. Obolenskii, I. Petrunkevich, and others to A. I. Konovalov and from V. Viktorov-Toporov to N. Teslenko, 1920-1921 (923)
  - Lists (893)
    - Groups included in the Partiia Narodnoi Svobody
    - Members of the Central Committee
  - Minutes of meetings (1053) (1085)
  - Press release, n.d. (1019)
  - Reports, 1920
    - "Kratkaia zapiska o deiatel'nosti Vnepartiinago Soveshchaniia Obshchestvennykh i Gosudarstvennykh deiatelei v gor. Sevastopole" (883)
    - "Kratkaia zapiska po bor'be s bol'shevizmom" (1059)
    - "Lozh Trotskago" (1047)
    - "Otchet o poezdke v Gallipoli kniazia Pavla Dolgorukova, v seredine dekabria 1920 goda" (899)
    - "Programma dlia sobiraniia svedenii..postradavshykh vo vremia russkoi revoliutsii" (919)
  - Resolutions
    - 1920
      - General
        - May 9, Sevastopol' (877)
        - July 16 (889)
      - "Postanovlenie...po pol'skomu voprosu"
    - 1921 August (1069)
- PARIZHSKAIA GRUPPA, 1920-1924.
  Minutes of meetings. Includes material related to the subjects discussed at the meeting
  - Full session (Box 2.)
    - 1920
      - May-June. Includes resolutions (Folder 1)
      - October-November (Folder 2)
    - 1921
      - January-March (Folder 3)
      - July. Includes B. Gurevich, "Proekt No.7" (Folder 4)
      - September. Includes "Soobshchenie parizhskoi gruppy partii narodnoi svobody po povodu proishedshego raskola gruppy" (Folder 5)
      - October (Folder 6)
      - November-December (Folder 7)
    - 1922
      - January. Includes "Zapiska po povodu proektov priznaniia sovetskoi vlasti.." (in Russian and French) (Folder 8)
      - February. Includes letters from A. Makletsov and A. Tyrkova and to G. Meingardt (Folder 9)
      - March. Includes printed matter and correspondence related to the death of V. D. Nabokov (Folder 10)
      - April. Includes correspondence re Genoa Conference and article by Claude Aulagnon, "La question russe à la veille de la Conférence de Gênes" (Folder 11)
      - May-December (Folder 12)
    - 1923
      - January-May (Folder 13)
      - June-July (Folder 14)
      - November-December (Folder 15)
    - 1924 February-July (Folder 16)
  - Committee meetings
    - 1920
      - May. Includes report, "Beseda A. I. Konovalova s M. V. Bernadskim" and letters of I. Petrunkevich and M. Vinaver to A. Konovalov (Folder 17)
      - June. Includes letters of N. Astrov, P. Butenko, IU. Grigorkov, A. Gurevich, F. Rodichev, and B. Savinkov (Folder 18-19)
      - July. Includes letters of P. Butenko, D. Grimm, and P. Iurenev (Folder 20)
      - August (Folder 21)
      - October-November. Includes memorandum of A. Konovalov, M. Vinaver and N. Volkov re Gen. P. Vrangel's Government of South Russia, "Dokladnaia zapiska predstavlennaia gen. Vrangeliu", and "Deklaratsiia russkago politicheskago komiteta v Pol'she" under signature of B. Savinkov et al. Also includes letters from N. Teslenko and A. Tyrkova (Folder 22-24)
      - December. Includes memorandum, "Chto delat' posle krymskoi katastrofy". Also includes letters of N. Astrov, P. Dolgorukii, A. Guchkov, A. Kartashev, E. Kedrin, S. Panina, S. Shtern, N. Teslenko (Box 3., Folder 1-2)
    - 1921
      - January. Includes bulletin, "Biulleten' Soveshchaniia Chlenov Uchreditel'nago Sobraniia". Also includes letters of N. Astrov, M. Fedorov, and N. Teslenko (Folder 3)
      - February. Includes resolutions of N. Semenov and the Yugoslav section of the party. Also includes letters of V. Burtsev, A. Konovalov, A. Makletsov, G. Meingardt, and P. Miliukov (Folder 4)
      - March. Includes clipping from Le Temps, "Zaivlenie Gen. Pelle Gen. Vrangeliu". Also includes letters of S. Bass, A. Bezchinskii, and A. Makletsov (Folder 5)
      - April. Includes "Memorandum, predstavlennyi frantsuzskomu pravitel'stvu predstaviteliami russkikh organizatsii v Parizhe" and letter to the French Minister of Foreign Affairs. Also includes letters of P. Iurenev, A. Lomshakov A. Makletsov, K. Sokolov, A. Tyrkova, and N. Volkov (Folder 6-7)
      - May-June. Includes letter to the editor of Poslednie Novosti from the Sophia group of the party (Folder 8)
      - July-August. Includes copies of the newspaper Put', July 3 and August 9 and letter to the editor of Poslednie Novosti. Also includes letters of IU. Kliuchnikov (Folder 9)
      - September. Includes copies of newspaper Poslednie Novosti, the August 20 and September 3, 11, and 21. Also includes lists of party members, memorandum "Obshchiia polozheniia programmy politicheskago ob"edinennago komiteta" and draft of resolution "Proekt rezoliutsii Parizhskago Komiteta Narodnoi Svobody" (Folder 10-11)
- APPENDIX.
  - Original register (Box 12.)